Finding Aid for Read Bain Papers, 1893-1972.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Read Bain papers 1893-1972
Bain, Read.
851005 Aa 2
Professor of Sociology at Miami University, Oxford, Ohio; vice-president, 1944, of the American Sociological Society; editor-in-chief, 1938-1942, of the American Sociological Review; President, 1945, of the Sociological Research Association; poetry editor, 1953-1957, of The Humanist; include correspondence, class notes, student essays, poetry, books and articles, and assorted miscellanea.
12 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Professor Bain (donor no. 4692 ) in 1968.
The collection is open to research.
Subjects:
American Sociological Association.; American sociological review.; Bain, Read, 1892-; The Humanist.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; Poetry.; Periodicals--Publishing.; Sociology.; Teachers--Ohio--Oxford.; Teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Adams, Brooks, 1848-1927.; Benedict, Ruth, 1887-1948.; Bernstein, Leonard, 1918-1990; Bliven, Bruce, 1889-1977.; Bradley, Omar Nelson, 1893-1981.; Bricker, John W. (John William), 1893-1986.; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973.; Cantril, Hadley, 1906-1969.; Cather, Willa, 1873-1947.; Catton, Bruce, 1899-1978; Ciardi, John, 1916-1986; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.; Havighurst, Walter, 1901-1994; Hayakawa, S. I. (Samuel Ichiyé), 1906-; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1841-1935.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Brown, Muriel Buck Humphrey.; Kinsey, Alfred C. (Alfred Charles), 1894-1956.; Kluckhohn, Clyde, 1905-1960.; Lausche, Frank John, 1895-1990; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951.; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974.; Malinowski, Bronislaw, 1884-1942.; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1892-1950.; Mills, C. Wright (Charles Wright), 1916-1962.; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.; Morse, Wayne L. (Wayne Lyman), 1900-1974.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990.; Odum, Howard Washington, 1884-1954.; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953.; Pollock, James K. (James Kerr), 1898-1968; Rickey, Branch, 1881-1965.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970.; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967.; Schlesinger, Arthur Meier, 1888-1965.; Ross, Edward Alsworth, 1866-1951.; Steinman, D. B. (David Barnard), 1886-1960.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Stuart, Jesse, 1906-1984.; Taft, Charles P. (Charles Phelps), 1897-1983; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Webb, Beatrice Potter, 1858-1943.; White, Leslie A., 1900-1975.
- Biographical/personal
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1893-1911 (Box 1)
    (include Davis Family letters)
  - 1916-1938, 18 folders (Box 1)
  - 1939-1940, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - 1941-1946, 21 folders (Box 3)
  - 1947-1959, 21 folders (Box 4)
  - 1960-1972, 17 folders (Box 5)
- Writings
  - Manuscripts of articles, reviews, etc., 9 folders (Box 6)
  - Manuscripts of articles, reviews, etc., 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Autobiographical writings
    - "The First Twenty Years" (Box 7)
    - "Five Score and More" (Box 7)
    - "One Man's Life" (Box 7)
    - "Old Note, Old Alec, and Eliza Ann" (Box 7)
    - Early drafts of autobiography (Box 7)
- Student materials
  - Student papers (Box 8)
  - Class notes: sociology and other topics, 10 folders (Box 8)
  - Notebook undated (Box 9)
    (include student essays)
  - Notebook, ca. 1917 (Box 9)
  - Notebook, ca. 1920 (Box 9)
  - Student diary November 1, 1912-June 14, 1913 (Box 9)
  - Student diary March 17, 1914-June 17, 1914 (Box 9)
  - Student diary September 19, 1914-June 27, 1915 (Box 9)
  - Student diary October 10, 1915-June 18, 1916 (Box 9)
  - Student diary July 1, 1916-July 17, 1917 (Box 9)
  - Dissertation notecards (Box 9)
- Poetry and Other Writings
  - Poetry, 8 folders (Box 10)
  - Poetry, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Poetry on Indians (Box 11)
  - Poetry entitled, "The Idiot's Tale and Other Poems" (Box 11)
  - Poetry of Ruth Ball (Box 11)
  - Poetry notebooks 1910-1912
    - Poetry notebook 1910-1914 (Box 11)
    - Poetry notebook 1914-1915 (Box 11)
    - Poetry notebook 1915-1916 (Box 11)
    - Poetry notebook 1916-1919 (Box 11)
    - Poetry notebook 1919-1921 (Box 11)
    - Poetry notebook 1921-1922 (Box 11)
  - Book: Continental Anthologies (1929); include Bain poetry (Box 11)
- Publications
  - Reprints of writings, 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Book: Sonnets of a Portrait-Painter (1922); include letter to Bain's wife written in the margins (Box 12)
  - Book: The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism by Max Weber (1958); include Bain's notes in the margins (Box 12)
  - Book: Trends in American Sociology (1929) (Box 12)
  - Book: Sociology: Introductory Readings (1962), including articles by Bain (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous
  - Notes used in speeches (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous professional papers, 2 folders (Box 12)
Partial Index to Correspondence
Adams, Brooks, 1848-1927.
Feb. 1, 1921, Feb. 17, 1921
Benedict, Ruth, 1887-1948.
Aug. 14, 1940
Bernstein, Leonard, 1918-
Jan. 27, 1958, Mar. 21, 1958
Bliven, Bruce, 1889-1977.
1926, Jan. 20, 1931, Jan. 18, 1935, 1936, 1940-1941, Sept. 20, 1944, Oct. 4, 1945
Bradley, Omar Nelson, 1893-
Oct. 5, 1946, Oct. 11, 1946
Bricker, John W. (John William), 1893-1986.
Jan. 18, 1941, Mar. 18, 1941, Mar. 14, 1941
Brown, Muriel Buck Humphrey
Jan. 27, 1967
Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstriker), 1892-1973.
Nov. 17, 1950
Cantril, Albert Hadley, 1906-1969.
Feb. 7, 1939, Feb. 13, 1939
Cather, Willa, 1873-1947.
Jan. 14, 1931, Sept. 25, 1931 (to WC), Oct. 22, 1931
Catton, Bruce, 1899-
Jan. 4, 1957
Ciardi, John, 1916-
1954-1957, 1959-1960, Dec. ?, 1961, Oct. 11, 1963, 1964, July 15, 1967
Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.
Dec. 29, 1920, 1922-1927
Dewey, John, 1859-1952.
Mar. 12, 1935, Nov. 28, 1936, Nov. 4, 1940, Oct. 25, 1949, Oct. 31, 1949, Oct. 31, 1950
Douglas, Paul Howard, 1892-
Apr. 21, 1953
Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.
Apr. 29, 1938, May 3, 1938?
Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.
Oct. 31, 1934, Nov. 25, 1934
Havighurst, Walter, 1901-
Nov. 1, 1961, Apr. 9, 1967
Hayakawa, S. I. (Samuel Ichiyé), 1906-
Nov. 15, 1957, Oct. 29, 1958, Oct. 1, 1958, May 21, 1963, May 8, 1963
Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1841-1935.
Apr. 27, 1927
Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.
Mar. 2, 1935, Sept. 26, 1936, Oct. 5, 1936, Apr. 4, 1939, Dec. 11, 1951, Dec. 4, 1951
Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.
Sept. 28, 1939, Oct. 10, 1939
Kinsey, Alfred C. (Alfred Charles), 1894-1956.
Aug. 15, 1952
Kluckhohn, Clyde, 1905-1960.
Oct. 16, 1944, Oct. 19, 1944
Lausche, Frank John, 1895-
Aug. 5, 1956, Oct. 8, 1956
Lewis, Sinclair, 1884-1951.
June 8, 1925
Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974.
undated
Malinowski, Bronislav, 1884-1942.
Apr. 29, 1939, Apr. 20, 1939, Apr. 12, 1939, Apr. 14, 1939
Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955.
June 8, 1938, Feb. 20, 1939, April 18, 1939, March 2, 1940, Sept. 18, 1944, Jan. 8, 1949, Mar. 18, 1952
Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.
undated
Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1892-1950.
undated
Mills, C. Wright (Charles Wright), 1916-1962.
1939-1940, July ?, 1942, July 30, 1945
Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.
Apr. 23, 1957, Dec. 3, 1964, Feb 13, 1965, Oct. 2, 1965, Feb. 19, 1966
Morse, Wayne Lyman, 1900-
May 31, 1962, June 11, 1962, Aug. 10, 1964, Aug. 28, 1964, Nov. 16, 1966, Oct. 10, 1967, May 28, 1968, June 12, 1968
Mumford, Lewis, 1895-
Jan. 19, 1935, Feb. 2, 1935, Feb. 9, 1935, Feb. 14, 1935
Odum, Howard Washington, 1884-1954.
June 8, 1925, Nov. 3, 1925, 1926, Aug. 15, 1927, May 11, 1933, Apr. 13, 1934, Nov. 28, 1936, Nov. 25, 1936, Jan. 18, 1938, Feb. 24, 1938, 1940, Mar. 17, 1941, Mar. 24, 1945
O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953.
July 7, 1933
Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-
July 25, 1938
Rickey, Branch, 1881-1965.
Oct. 25, 1945, Nov. 9, 1945
Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.
Oct. 25, 1957, Oct. 31, 1957
Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.
Aug. 20, 1932, Jan. 4, 1939
Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970.
May 25, 1951, May 8, 1951
Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967.
Aug. 31, 1922, June 23, 1955, June 14, 1960
Schlesinger, Arthur Meier, 1888-1965.
June 5, 1939, July 20, 1939, Oct. 21, 1939, Dec. 9, 1939, Jan. 6, 1940, Mar. 5, 1940
Steinman, D. B. (David Barnard), 1886-1960.
1945-1946, Nov. 10, 1956, Nov. 29, 1956, Dec. 8, 1956, Dec. 4, 1956
Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.
Nov. 8, 1960, Jan. 11, 1961
Stuart, Jesse Hilton, 1906-1984
1937, Oct. 8, 1938, 1939, Dec. 18, 1943, 1944, May 10, 1949, 1955, Jan. 29, 1957, 1958, 1960, 1965, Sept. 3, 1968
Taft, Charles Phelps, 1897-
Mar. 31, 1939, May 29, 1940, May 25, 1940, 1951-1952, Mar. 4, 1954, Oct. 31, 1955, Dec. ?, 1955
Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.
Jan. 20, 1952, Feb. 10, 1953
Webb, Beatrice Potter, 1858-1943.
Apr. 30, 1926, Apr. 16, 1926
White, Leslie A., 1900-1975.
July 22, 1939, July 1, 1939, Nov. 29, 1940, Jan. 3, 1941, Feb. 24, 1943